Guide to the Hyman I. Feldman Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Hyman I. Feldman records
1900-1981
MS 1887
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9
(9 boxes)
This collection documents the work of architect and Yale School of Architecture graduate Hyman I. Feldman. It includes student work, photographs, writings, awards, and scrapbooks pertaining to his life and work, and ledgers, photographs, correspondence, and specifications documenting many of his architectural projects, especially his work at Yeshiva University.
Feldman, Hyman I.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials are a gift of Naomi Fatouros, 2006.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Hyman Isaac Feldman was born in Szczerzec, now Ukraine, in 1897 and emigrated with his family to New York when he was four years old. He attended City College and Cornell University, where he studied landscape architecture. He enrolled at Yale University, left to join the Army, and returned after World War I to complete his degree in architecture in 1919. In 1921 he established an architectural practice in New York, and designed over 2,500 developer-built apartment buildings in the metropolitan area. He also designed buildings for the New York City Housing Authority and the Federation of Jewish Philanthropies of New York. He endowed the H. I. Feldman Scholarship in Architecture at Yale, and received honorary degrees in architecture from City College and Columbia University. Feldman died in New York at the age of 84 on January 26, 1981.
Scope and Contents
This collection documents the work of architect and Yale School of Architecture graduate Hyman I. Feldman. It includes student work, photographs, writings, awards, and scrapbooks pertaining to his life and work, and ledgers, photographs, correspondence, and specifications documenting many of his architectural projects, especially his work at Yeshiva University.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged in two series: I. Biographical, circa 1900-1986. II. Project Records, circa 1921-1981.
Apartment houses; Feldman, Hyman I.; Yeshiva University
- Biographical, Circa 1900-1981; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes student work, photographs, writings, awards and scrapbooks documenting Feldman's personal life and professional work as an architect.
  - Student work, Circa 1917-1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Personal materials, 1911-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Professional organizations, 1923-1969 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, Circa 1900-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Awards and degrees, 1920-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Writings: Real Estate News, 1934 December-1935 July (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Writings: Real Estate News, 1935 August-1939 July (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Circa 1926-1939 (Box 2, Folder 5-6)
    - Circa 1931-1951, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Circa 1933-1969 (Box 3, Folder 2-6)
- Project records, Circa 1921-1981; Series II
  This series includes ledgers, photographs, correspondence, and specifications for many projects, particularly pertaining to Feldman's work at Yeshiva University.
  - Project record index, 1935-1971 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Time/cost ledgers
    - Circa 1944-1966 Circa 1944-1966 Circa 1944-1966 (Box 4, Folder 2-5)
    - 1947-1969 1947-1969 1947-1969 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
      Includes cash receipts, disbursements, and personal finances.
    - 1947-1969 1947-1969 1947-1969 (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
    - 1929-1936 1929-1936 1929-1936 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Project photographs, Circa 1921-1981 (Box 5, Folder 4-7)
  - Negatives, Circa 1921-1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Project ephemera, Circa 1926-1959 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Yeshiva University
    - Job correspondence, Circa 1963-1974 (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
    - Legal documents, 1963-1970 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
    - Dormitory specifications, addenda, and bid forms, 1962-1963 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
    - Stern College for Women specification and addenda, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - Proposal for Delmonico's site, New York, NY, 1926 (Box 8)
  - Park Lane Tower, New York, NY, Circa 1960-1979 (Box 9)